Guide to the Heraldo Muñoz Papers, 1963-2013 and undated RL.00920
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Heraldo Muñoz papers
1963-2013 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Muñoz, Heraldo
RL.00920
8.2 Linear Feet 16 boxes; 1 oversize folder Approximately 5800 items
Chilean politician, diplomat, author, and ambassador to the United Nations. Spanning the period of 1963 to 2013, the Heraldo Muñoz Papers contain materials related to Muñoz's work as a researcher and diplomat, and his role in the Chilean Socialist Party. Primarily consisting of handwritten notes, correspondence, reports, policy documents, printed materials, and electronic files, the collection emphasizes Chilean domestic and international politics from 1970 to 2010 (including the 1973 coup and the Pinochet dictatorship) and the United Nations' (UN) work on sanctions, counter-terrorism, and peacebuilding from 2003 to 2013. The collection is organized into the following series: Charles Horman Case Files, Chile - Domestic Politics; Chile - Foreign Policy; Correspondence and Clippings; International Work; Memorabilia; Photographs; and Commission of Inquiry. The largest group of materials relate to Muñoz's work at the UN.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Heraldo Muñoz Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010, 2011, 2012, and 2014.
Biographical Note
Born in Santiago, Chile on July 22, 1948, Heraldo Muñoz Valenzuela received a B.A. in Political Science from the State University of New York at Oswego in 1972. At the time of the 1973 coup that overthrew Chilean President Salvador Allende, Muñoz was serving as National Supervisor of People's Stores in the Allende administration. In 1975, he received a diploma in International Relations from Catholic University of Chile. Muñoz was a fellow the Brookings Institute in Washington, D.C. in 1977 and received his Ph.D. in International Studies from the University of Denver in 1978.
From 1983 to 1986, Muñoz was Secretary for International Relations of the Chilean Socialist Party and was a member of the Executive Committee for the "no" vote in the 1988 plebiscite on extending the rule of dictator Augusto Pinochet. After the return to democracy, President Patricio Aylwin appointed Muñoz to be Chile's Ambassador to the Organization of American States (OAS) in Washington, D.C. (1990-1994). After the election of Eduardo Frei in 1994, Muñoz served as Ambassador to Brazil. He left this post in 1998 to become the Coordinator of Foreign Relations for Ricardo Lagos's presidential campaign. After Lagos's election, Muñoz served in his administration as Deputy Minister of Foreign Relations (2000-2002) and as Minister Secretary General of Government (2002-2003).
In 2003, Lagos appointed Muñoz to be Chile's Ambassador to the United Nations (UN). At the UN, Muñoz was Chairman of the Al-Qaeda and Taliban Sanctions Committee (1267 Committee) from 2003 to 2004 and was on the Security Council in 2004, holding the presidency during the month of January. He also served as Vice-President of the General Assembly's 61st session (2006-2007), as Chairman of the Working Group on Security Council Reform (2007-2008), and as Chairman of the UN Peacebuilding Commission (2009). After the election of President Sebastián Piñera in 2010, Muñoz left the ambassadorship and became the Director of the Regional Bureau for Latin America at the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) and UN Assistant Secretary General.
Muñoz is the author and editor of numerous volumes on international relations and Chilean politics, including Elusive Friendship: A Survey of U.S.-Chilean Relations (1991), Democracy Rising: Assessing the Global Challenges (2006), A Solitary War: A Diplomat's Chronicle of the Iraq War and its Lessons (2008), and The Dictator's Shadow: Life Under Augusto Pinochet (2008).
Collection Overview
Spanning the period of 1963 to 2013, the Heraldo Muñoz Papers contain materials related to Muñoz's work as a researcher and diplomat, and his role in the Chilean Socialist Party. Primarily consisting of handwritten notes, correspondence, reports, policy documents, printed materials, and electronic files, the collection emphasizes Chilean domestic and international politics from 1970 to 2010 (including the 1973 coup and the Pinochet dictatorship) and the United Nations' (UN) work on sanctions, counter-terrorism, and peacebuilding from 2003 to 2010. The collection is organized into the following series: Charles Horman Case Files; Chile - Domestic Politics; Chile - Foreign Policy; Correspondence and Clippings; International Work; Memorabilia; Photographs; and Commssion of Inquiry.
Largest in the collection is the International Work Series, which primarily contains notes, reports, and speeches from Muñoz's work at the UN. Organized into subseries on UN Reform, the UN Security Council, and other materials, the bulk of this documentation relates to Muñoz's chairmanship of the Al-Qaeda and Taliban Sanctions Committee (1267 Committee) from 2003 to 2004. The Charles Horman Case Files Series primarily contains photocopies of Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests by the Horman family and the responsive documents produced by U.S. agencies regarding the murder of US journalist Charles Horman during the 1973 military coup in Chile. Muñoz obtained these documents from Horman's widow Joyce as part of his research for In the Dictator's Shadow. The Chile - Domestic Politics Series contains correspondence, internal Socialist Party documents, and materials produced by the opposition prior to the 1988 plebiscite on extending the rule of dictator Augusto Pinochet. The Chile - Foreign Policy Series contains documents and correspondence related to Muñoz's work in the Lagos campaign and administration, and as ambassador to the OAS, Brazil, and the UN. Particularly noteworthy are documents related to Pinochet's arrest in the UK. Programs, invitations, and passes mostly related to Muñoz's international work make up the Memorabilia Series. Containing both print and electronic documents, the Photographs Series also primarily depicts Muñoz's work at the UN through publicity shots and snapshots. The Writings and Research Series contains Muñoz's research, speeches, articles, and notes on Augusto Pinochet, U.S. and Chilean politics, and international governance. Although much of Muñoz's correspondence is integrated into the series to which it relates, the Correspondence and Clippings Series spans his professional career. Noteworthy correspondents include: Ricardo Lagos, Pascal Lamy, Thomas F. MacLarty III, Condoleezza Rice, Barbara Walters, and Timothy E. Wirth.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Human Rights -- Chile -- History -- 20th century; Freedom of Information -- Chile; Chile -- Relations -- United States; Chile -- Foreign relations -- 1988-; United Nations Peacebuilding Commission; Posters; Plebiscite -- Chile; Photographs; United Nations. Security Council; United States -- Relations -- Chile; United Nations -- Reform; Chile -- Politics and government -- 1988-; Chile -- Politics and government -- 1973-1988 -- Periodicals; Chile -- Politics and government -- 1973-1988; United Nations -- Sanctions; Bachelet, Michelle, 1951-; Horman, Charles, 1942-1973; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Lagos, Ricardo A., 1969-; Muñoz, Heraldo; Partido Comunista de Chile; Partido por la Democracia (Chile); Partido Socialista (Chile); Pinochet Ugarte, Augusto
- Charles Horman Case Files Series, 1973-1993 and undated, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Primarily contains photocopies of Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests by the Horman family and the responsive documents produced by U.S. agencies regarding the murder of US journalist Charles Horman during the 1973 military coup in Chile. Muñoz obtained these documents from Horman's widow Joyce as part of his research for In the Dictator's Shadow. FOIA materials are arranged by date of the original document. Also included are photocopies of public statements, clippings, House sub-committee testimony, materials related to the production of the film Missing, and the Horman family's correspondence and notes regarding the case. FOIA materials appear first, followed by supporting materials.
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) records, 1973-1977, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - FOIA lists, undated (Box 1)
  - Comments on FOIA lists, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Department of State (DOS) public statements, 1974 Jan.-Feb. (Box 1)
  - FOIA requests to DOS, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - FOIA appeal to DOS, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - FOIA requests to Department of Defense (DOD), 1976 July-Sept. (Box 1)
  - FOIA requests to Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - FOIA requests to U.S. Postal Service (USPS), 1977 Dec. (Box 2)
  - Materials for scanning, 1974-1979 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1973-1979, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Congressional correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Missing (film), 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Missing libel case opinion, 1987 Mar. 2 (Box 2)
- Chile - Domestic Politics Series, 1977-1993, 2 boxes
  Contains documents produced by the Chile Socialist Party, the Communist Party, and the Party for Democracy (PPD) prior to and during the 1988 plebiscite on extending Pinochet's rule. Materials include articles, clippings, party platforms, party communications, mailings, Socialist Party internal planning documents and reports, materials from national and international socialist meetings, handwritten notes, Muñoz's correspondence with Chilean and international politicians, instructions and manuals for the plebiscite, selected plebiscite voting results, "get out the vote" materials, and copies of classified Chilean Ministry of Foreign Relations communications with the U.S. In addition to the plebiscite and internal party politics, the materials address the forming of the PPD and a commission on human rights. Mixed in are political pamphlets and periodicals, including editions of Historia documental del Partido Socialista de Chile, Unidad y lucha, and Boletin del Comité Central del Partido Socialista de Chile. Arranged chronologically with significant overlapping content in Opposition to Pinochet and Socialist Party folders.
  - Opposition to Pinochet, 1977, 1983-1988, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Socialist Party, 1983-1987, 3 of 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Socialist Party, 1984-1989, 8 of 11 folders (Box 3)
  - Programa de seguimiento de las políticas exteriores latinoamericanas limitada (PROSPEL), 1985-1993 (Box 3)
  - Printed materials, 1990-1993, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Aylwin Azócar, Patricio. Amanece en Chile. [Santiago]: Ministerio Secretaría General de Gobierno, 1990. (Box 3)
    - Chile. Presidencia de la República. Chile 1991. [Santiago]: Presidencia de la República, 1991. (Box 3)
    - Comisión Chilena de Derechos Humanos and Centro IDEAS. Síntesis del informe de la Comisión Verdad y Reconciliación. Santiago: Comisión Chilena de Derechos Humanos, Centro IDEAS, 1991. (Box 3)
    - Meller, Patricio. Resultados económicos de cuatro gobiernos chilenos 1958-1989. Santiago: Apuntes CIEPLAN no. 89, 1990. (Box 3)
    - Herzberg, Julia P. Recovering Histories: Aspects of Contemporary Art in Chile Since 1982. New Brunswick, NJ: Centro Latino de Arte y Cultura, 1993. (Box 3)
    - Salvador Allende political posters, 1988, 2 items (Oversize-folder OV MSS Box Run B:7, Oversize-folder 1)
    - Oversize newspaper clippings, opposition to Pinochet and Socialist Party, 9 items, plus 1 duplicate; box dimensions: 14x18 inches (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Unidad y Lucha newspapers, 1986-1989, 23 items, plus 1 duplicate (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - "Programa de seguimiento de las politicas exteriores latinoamericanas limitada," notarized PROSPEL document, 1989, 1 item (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Chile - Foreign Policy Series, 1987-2009 and undated, 3 boxes
  Contains Chile foreign policy documents that derive from Muñoz's work in the Lagos campaign and administration, and as ambassador to the Organization for American States (OAS), Brazil, and the United Nations (UN). Materials include correspondence, speeches, notes, clippings, articles, conference programs, copies of photographs, political lists, pamphlets, internal policy documents, communications with foreign governments, and travel itineraries. Some of Ricardo Lago's correspondence with foreign dignitaries is also included. Also contains a signed copy of the 1995 Itamaraty Peace Declaration, which fulfilled the 1942 Rio Protocol, and confidential correspondence regarding foreign policy and Pinochet's arrest in the U.K. Arranged chronologically.
  - Convention against Torture, 1987, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Ambassador to the Organization of American States (OAS), 1990-1994, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Ambassador to OAS, memos from Ministry of Foreign Relations, 1990-1994 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1990-1998 and undated (Box 4)
  - Ambassador to Brazil, 1994-1998, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Pinochet arrest, 1998-2000 (Box 4)
  - Lagos campaign, 1999-2000, 2 of 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Lagos campaign, 1999-2000, 1 of 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Yoko Ono visit, 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - Positions and interviews, 1999-2003 (Box 5)
  - Ministry of Foreign Relations - ambassadors, 2000 Feb.-Mar. (Box 5)
  - European Union (EU) negotiations, 2000 Apr. 10-11 (Box 5)
  - King of Spain visit, 2000 June 20-22 (Box 5)
  - Ministry of Foreign Relations - fishing rights and miscellaneous, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Ministry of Foreign Relations - speeches and notes, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Ministry of Foreign Relations - transfer of power and EU negotiations, 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Ministry of Foreign Relations and Minister Secretary General, 2000-2002, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Reserved documents, 2000-2009, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - WTO Conference in Doha, 2001 Nov., 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Terrorism, 2001-2005 (Box 6)
  - Cuba communications, 2002 and undated (Box 6)
  - Ministry Secretary General - sports professional corporations, 2002 (Box 6)
  - Lagos N.Y. visits, 2004 July-Sept. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 2003-2006 (Box 6)
  - Positions and agreements, 2004-2009 (Box 6)
  - Bachelet N.Y. visit, 2005 Jan. 10-14 (Box 6)
  - Security Council vote, 2007 (Box 6)
  - Bali climate change conference, 2007 Nov. 28 (Box 6)
  - Presentation and conference program, 2007-2009 (Box 6)
  - UNASUR and Rio Group policy, 2008 Sept. (Box 6)
  - U.N. policy, 2008 Sept. (Box 6)
  - Summit on climate change, 2009 Sept. 21-23 (Box 6)
  - Hard-bound copy of Itamaraty Peace Declaration, 1995, 1 item; box dimensions: 14x18 inches (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Correspondence and Clippings Series, 1976-2010, 2 boxes
  Contains mostly correspondence but also invitations, notes, lectures, conference programs, some policy documents, and clippings of newspaper articles as well as Muñoz's own writings and interviews. Topics include his academic work in international studies and political science, and his positions in the Socialist Party, the Lagos administration, and as ambassador to the OAS, Brazil, and the UN. Noteworthy correspondents (most represented by only a few items each) include: Fernando Henrique Cardoso, Patricio Aylwin, Eduardo Frei, Michelle Bachelet, Isabel Allende, Jaime Paz Zamora, Desmond Tutu, Kofi Annan, Barbara Walters, Yoko Ono, Hillary Rodham Clinton, John Negroponte, and Condoleezza Rice. More numerically substantial is Muñoz's correspondence with Ricardo Lagos, Pascal Lamy, Thomas F. MacLarty III, and Timothy E. Wirth. Arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1976-2003 (Box 6)
  - Interviews and articles clippings, 1983-2001 (Box 6)
  - Latin America clippings, 1985-2000 (Box 6)
  - Academic, OAS, and Brazil correspondence and clippings, 1988-1997, 1 of 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Academic, OAS, and Brazil correspondence and clippings, 1988-1997, 2 of 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Chile correspondence and clippings, 2000-2003 (Box 7)
  - International work and publications correspondence, 2003-2010 (Box 7)
  - International work clippings, 2002-2009 (Box 7)
- International Work Series, 2003-2009, 5 boxes
  Contains documents related to Muñoz's international work at the UN, including his presidency of the Security Council, chairmanship of the Al-Qaeda and Taliban Sanctions Committee (1267 Committee), work on the Peacebuilding Commission, and participation in committees to reform the UN. Materials include drafts, position papers, memos, proposals, presentations, official correspondence, reports, speeches, articles, clippings, resolutions, statements, minutes, interviews, itineraries, copies of photographs, pamphlets, business cards, and conference and meeting programs and notes. Many of the documents have handwritten annotations. Also included is confidential correspondence regarding Chilean foreign policy. Topics include: UN reform, human rights, international security, peacebuilding, the financial crisis, Iraq, Iran, Israel, Sudan, Somalia, and Haiti. Three subseries on UN Reform, UN Security Council, and other materials are each arranged chronologically.
  - UN Reform, 2005-2009
    - Group of Friends, 2005, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Group of Friends meeting in Santiago, Chile, 2005 May 6-7 (Box 7)
    - Group of Friends meeting in Cartegena, Colombia, 2006 May 5-6 (Box 7)
    - System-wide coherence meeting, 2006 Apr. 4-6 (Box 7)
    - System-wide coherence, 2007-2008 (Box 7)
    - G-4 meeting notes, 2007 (Box 8)
    - Security Council Reform, 2007-2009, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Security Council Reform report, 2008 (Box 8)
  - UN Security Council, 2003-2004
    - Security Council, 2003-2004, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Security Council Presidency, 2004 Jan., 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Cyprus, 2004 Apr. 20-21 (Box 8)
    - Philippines visit, 2004 Oct. 6 (Box 8)
    - Security Council meeting in Nairobi, 2004 Nov. 18-19 (Box 8)
    - 1267 Committee visit to Afghanistan, the United Arab Emirates, Singapore, and Indonesia, 2003 Oct. 10-23, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1267 Committee visit to Belgium, Liechtenstein, Italy, Pakistan, and Saudi Arabia, 2003 Dec. 1-8 (Box 9)
    - 1267 Committee visit to Algeria, Tunisia, Spain, and Senegal, 2004 May 1-8 (Box 9)
    - 1267 Committee - Cambodia, 2004 Sept.-Dec. (Box 9)
    - 1267 Committee visit to Philippines, Cambodia, Thailand, and Australia, 2004 Oct. 4-14 (Box 9)
    - 1267 Committee visit to Libya, Iran, and Switzerland, 2004 Dec. 4-10 (Box 9)
    - 1267 Committee, 2003-2004, 2 of 9 folders (Box 9)
    - 1267 Committee, 2003-2004, 7 of 9 folders (Box 10)
    - Workshop on sanctions reform, 2003 May 2-3 (Box 10)
    - Bali regional meeting on counter-terrorism, 2005 Feb. 4-5 (Box 10)
  - Other Materials 2003-2009
    - Miscellaneous documents, 2003-2005 (Box 10)
    - Community of Democracies, 2003-2005 (Box 10)
    - Haiti, 2004-2005 (Box 10)
    - UN - human rights, 2004-2008 (Box 10)
    - Terrorism, 2004-2008 (Box 10)
    - United Nations of the Next Decade conference in Portugal, 2008 June 20-25 (Box 11)
    - International security conferences, 2008 Oct. (Box 11)
    - Peacebuilding Commission, 2008-2009, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Peacebuilding Commission retreat, 2009 Feb. 6-7 (Box 11)
    - Peacebuilding Commission visit to Addis Ababa, 2009 Nov. 7-9 (Box 11)
    - Haiti Donors Conference, 2009 Apr. 14 (Box 11)
    - UN conference on financial crisis, 2009 Jun. 24-26 (Box 11)
- Memorabilia Series, 1963-2010, 6 folders
  Contains programs, invitations, passes, and identification cards for Muñoz's international work and events such as inaugurations, benefits, and presidential visits. Also included is Muñoz's 1966 passport and copies of school documents from 1963. Arranged by type of material and then chronologically.
  - Identification and passes, 1966, 1992-2010 (Box 11)
  - Programs, 1990-2009, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Programs and invitations, 1992-2010 (Box 11)
  - Student evaluation, certificate, and programs related to conferences and speaking engagements, 1963, 1996-2010 (Box 12)
  - Commemorative map of Southern Chile cruise, inscribed to Muñoz and signed by Almirante Jorge Reyes, Comandante en Jefe de la Armada, 2000, 1 item (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Photographs Series, circa 1980-2009 and undated, 33 prints and 196 digital files
  Arranged in original order as received, prints and digital files are chiefly publicity shots related to Muñoz's international work. Shots depict Muñoz with family members, with colleagues at various events, and playing soccer. Among others portrayed in the images are Ricardo Lagos, Michelle Bachelet, Patricio Aylwin, Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva, Ban Ki-moon, Kofi Annan, George and Barbara Bush, George W. Bush, Condoleezza Rice, and Al Gore.
  - Photographic prints, 2001-2009 and undated (Box 12)
  - Digital photograph files, 196 files, 255.3 MB
    Arranged in original order as received, digital photographs are separated into two electronic folders on a library server. Folder "091008_1327" contains 61 digital photographs of Muñoz and other attendees at a Celebration of Hispanic Heritage Month event in New York City on October 7, 2009, which featured Chilean textiles and was sponsored by the Gabriela Mistral Foundation. Folder "Amb_Munoz_photos" contains 135 files (some of which contain more than one scanned photograph) that date from various points in Muñoz's career.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    [Electronic files have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
    - Digital photographs Hispanic Heritage Month celebration, New York City, October 7, 2009, 61 files (E-folder 091008_1327)
    - Digital photographs of Muñoz, 135 files (E-folder Amb_Munoz_photos)
- Writings and Research Series, 1970-2010 and undated, 2 boxes and 1 electronic file
  Contains Muñoz's research, speeches, articles, and notes, many with handwritten annotations. Research materials include clippings, meeting notes, publications, speeches, legal analysis, opinion polls, copies of classified Chilean Ministry of Foreign Relations and U.S. State Department communications, and copies of photographs. Topics covered include: Augusto Pinochet, Salvador Allende, Orlando Letelier, Charles Horman, Carlos Berger, Operation Colombo, CIA activities, U.S.-Latin American relations, U.S. and Chilean politics, international governance, human rights, and transitional justice. Two subseries on Pinochet Research and Articles, Speeches, and Notes are each arranged chronologically.
  - Articles, Speeches, and Notes, 1983-2010 and undated
    - Socialism article draft, 1983 (Box 12)
    - Notes - U.S. policy in Chile, undated (Box 12)
    - Speeches and articles - democracy, 1993-2009 (Box 12)
    - Speeches and articles, 1999-2010 (Box 12)
    - U.S.-Latin America notes and articles, 2003-2007 (Box 12)
    - The United States and Latin America in the Context of the Iraq Crisis, 2003 Apr. 4 (E-folder Disk 001)
      [Electronic file has been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Pinochet Research, 1970-2008
    - Pinochet research, 1970-2008, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - American-Chilean Council registration, 1977 (Box 12)
    - Communist Party, 1981-2006 (Box 13)
    - Letelier case - Chile response, 1990 Nov. 30 (Box 13)
    - Pinochet letter, 1999 Sept. 11 (Box 13)
    - Riggs Bank, 2004-2005 (Box 13)
    - Pinochet family indictment, 2007 Oct. 4 (Box 13)
- Accession (2012-0111), 1972-2012